Guide to the Robert Grenier Papers
Department of Special Collections
- Series VIII. RG Book Manuscripts 1967 - 1997, Drafts and finished versions of various texts, dated/chronologized and counted (by pages of text) in folders and binders - 2 boxes.
  - W. History of making of RG issue of :that:, No. 24 (August 1994), (86 pp. total) (Box 019)
    - 1. 100% black/white xerox 'masters' of sequence of 28 pages from RG color holograph notebook drawing poems
    - 2. 64% black/white xerox reductions from 'master' images to scale/to fit magazine & darken images
    - 3. Issue of :that:, No. 24 made from images provided by RG
  - X. History of development of RG critical work, FOR LESLIE SCALAPINO'S DEFOE, 1995, (157 pp. total) (Box 019)
    Combining citations from Defoe (Sun & Moon Press, 1994) w/ RG observations, Wanda Landowska liner notes, poems by Whitman & Williams, RG color holograph drawing poems & other materials.
    - 1. RG holograph first draft
    - 2. RG ts. second draft
    - 3. RG ts./xerox final draft
  - Y. Black/white print-out of color images in RG poem sequence, POND I, January 8, 1998, (43 pp. total) (Box 019)
    From Karl Young's Light & Dust website, w/ Karl Young introduction.
- Series IX. Histories of Making/Production of RG Works 1971 - 1997, Material records of RG's invention/development of the following artifacts: A. SENTENCES-1 box; B. A DAY AT THE BEACH - 1 box; C. PHANTOM ANTHEMS -1 box; D. WHAT I BELIEVE TRANSPIRATION/TRANSPIRING MINNESOTA -1 box; E. OWL/ON/BOU/GH -approx. 200 11" by 17" color xeroxes.
  Comment: Beginning w/ the (unpublished) 'UR' version of ms. called A DAY AT THE BEACH (see VIII.F. & G. above), one can see RG beginning to recognize/zero in on the material conditions/situation of writing as the 'place' of 'literature' (doubtless influenced by William Carlos Williams' mysterious emphasis on whatever is the 'local' & by 'opening his eyes'), both as regards writing directly from noticing what's 'going on' & in re having a regard for the literal/physical agencies used (notebooks, pens, etc.) to 'say something' into existence & to translate/ manifest 'same' into (further) public existence: there's responsibility to carry the thing through from start to finish, so that whatever it is can be whatever it is (including this inventory). Therefore, a (good!) case can be made that each work 'exists' here (in this Archive) in the facts of its making (see esp. IX.B. below) as well as in its eventual result (for which, see section XII below, RG Published Works). Material records of RG's making of CAMBRIDGE M'ASS should be here, except there's no 'history' (but see VII.M. & N. above) since large offset master was devoured in printing process (unless preserved in archives of Lyn Hejinian's Tuumba Press?) More importantly, RG's approximately 90 4-color holograph drawing poem notebooks from 1989 - 1999 (& continuing) must be here, eventually, as artifacts/'the thing itself' because of problems/expense of various techniques of 'reproduction' (but see slides in section XI. below) & because drawn image in notebook now is 'what it is' ! The main thing is recognition that something is 'said' & 'exists' exactly in that form entirely: e.g. IBM.
  Selectric typewriter image (like this one) or in RG Drawing 'hand' writing. Similar histories could be developed based on RG's commitment to a 'craft ethic'/ making of various other works in this Archive, e.g. attention to particulars of transcription of taped sounds in many of the materials in V.C. above (e.g., see stuff re RG Conversation w/ David Bromige in V.C.7. above) & attention to particulars of translation of notebook drawing poems to magazine presentation/format in re production of RG issue of :that:, No. 24 (VIII.W. above).
  In what follows, short descriptions of the works noted are succeeded by accounts of Archive materials related thereto and brief commentaries on the whole business.
  - A. SENTENCES, 1 box
    SENTENCES was designed/produced by RG & pub. by Michael Waltuch (Whale Cloth Press, 1978) in an edition of 200 (numbered) copies. It's 500 5" by 8" index cards w/ centered RG poems on them (in effect, as an 'invented form', giving back to the Oxford Index Card Company the 500 index cards that one bought, except w/ poems on them) 'bound' in a folding Chinese (Hong Kong/common) box, blue (then inexpensive/purchased through MW 'connection' through Harvard Far East Studies/Widener Library where he worked), widely used for loose-leaved materials. It was (offset) printed by the Harvard University Press (which was a 'gas' to RG at the time) directly from RG IBM Selectric (Courier 72/10 pitch) typewriter images & collated by RG, MW, John Bátki & students in JB's fiction writing class at Harvard College in the Spring of 1978 (by going round & round the stacks of 506 on seminar tables) as a 'lesson to them'.
    - 1. Oxford index Card box w/ "SENTENCES REJECTS / April 3/77" on top (card on top of stack inside box says (crossed-out) "April 1/75, Sept 5/75, Sept. 20/76"), containing 462 5" by 8" index cards (231 poems + 1 other of each) w/ RG poems (Box 020)
    - 2. Oxford index Card box w/ "SENTENCES REJECTS / September 20/77" on top, containing 454 cards (227 poems + duplicates) (Box 020)
    - 3. Oxford index Card box w/ "SENTENCES REJECTS / OCTOBER 9/77" on top (card on top of stack inside box says (crossed-out) "Sept. 5/75, Sept. 20/76, April 3/77"), containing 512 cards (256 poems + duplicates) (Box 020)
    - 4. Oxford index Card box w/ "BEST SENTENCES POSSIBILITIES" / October 25/77, On top, containing 390 cards (Box 020)
      - "best SENTENCES possibilities" (Oct. 25/77), being, 8 single poems (8 cards), 48 poems (+ duplicates) (96 cards)
      - and "less interesting", being
        "Sentences rejects (Oct. 26/77)", being 160 cards (80 poems + duplicates) & "Sentences rejects / 11/30/77", being 126 cards (63 poems + duplicates)
    - 5. Oxford index Card box w/ "SENTENCES / RG Master Set / 500 Poems / (11/30/77)" on top, being RG ts. final version of this work, minus colophon page (502 cards total), from which a second edition could be produced (actual RG ts. cards from which first edition were made devoured in offset printing process in 1978, see photo in A.6. below) (Box 020)
    - 6. 10 photographs documenting SENTENCES project: (1971-78) (Box 020)
      - 8 photos of RG show at Franconia College, Franconia, NH in Spring 1972 of early SENTENCES poems on 5" by 8" index cards on walls of gallery space
      - 1 aerial photo of Franconia College in early 1970's
        (where RG taught, 1971-76)
      - 1 photo of Michael Waltuch & RG laying out 5" by 8" SENTENCES index cards on sheets for photo-offset reproduction by Harvard U. Press, Cambridge, MA in early Spring 1978
    - 7. 204 slides taken in Franconia, NH in 1975 of RG Selectric ts. images on 5" by 8" index cards, being 'mounted negatives' (so that text appears white/light against grey ground) which document state of SENTENCES project in 1975, (in 4 slide boxes w/ 51 slides each) (Box 020)
      Are 'works in themselves'/alternate material embodiments of SENTENCES text which were shown by Bob Perelman in San Francisco on July 14, 1977 to interested persons at the beginning of the Language Writing scene in SF & again shown & interpreted by RG during RG talk series "Language/Site/ World" in SF in Fall 1982 (see V.A.3 & V.C.2 above)
      COMMENT: SENTENCES was written over a 7-year period, beginning in Spring 1971 in Lanesville (Gloucester), MA (during/after completion of RG's Series, see RG ts. in VIII.K. above) & continuing/focussing into itself in Franconia & Sugar Hill, NH (where RG went to teach at Franconia College, Fall 1971-Spring 1976) (increasingly bearing direct relation to/seeming 'of'/'from' that isolate/clearly defined/attractive but repugnant/silent/'substantial' but elusive/cold/'compelling'/dreamily beautiful & strange-place (e.g. hot day jumping off granite boulders into freezing Pemigewasset/swimming to live to shore), where words (if words) were (equally) solitary/as if composed entirely of particular ('solid') letters made into words, which were 'of the place' but 'only of language itself' at the same time), w/ a few from Oakland & Bolinas, CA & some (later ones) from RG's residency in Cambridge, MA (Fall 1976-Spring 1978). It's an attempt to 'stop Time'/'destroy the Book' in reaction to method (apparently achieved/'over with') of Robert Creeley's beloved Pieces (or, e.g., "Sticky Fingers" in RG's own Series) (see RG note on Pieces in VI.C. 4 above), to let each (anything) be that one (& not 'rush on'), but it still has to do w/ time w/in/across each letter-made poem but (almost/as if) just moving left-to-right cross space (as in poem "kept on going to the corner store") & also ends up being an 'investigation of narrative structure' (despite avowed (?)/apparent attempt to eschew such) (various 'stories' must be made by each reader, seeing different one-after-the-others by turning cards to read, loose-leaved cards) (see Ron Silliman's review of this work in III.B.22 above) & 'continuation of the story' 'of Bob, Emily & Amy' going on in RG's long poem, "Fall/ Winter Family Home" in Series, except different stories/thousands of them happen necessarily & continuingly/ continuously (potentially) or 'happen at once'. The form of SENTENCES has a lot to do w/ the IBM Selectric Typewriter, which was the 'Office Machine' in the early 1970's--i.e. one could see every word composed of equal ('width' & 'value') letters (see RG Conversation w/ Alastair Johnston in V.C.5. above) & led to 'early recognition' of principle-becoming-innate-recognition of counting letters as compositional method (see Ron Silliman emphasis on 'balance' in review of SENTENCES noted above) (out of Louis Zukofsky's line determined by # of words in the late A?). After much other stuff, this noticing of space (long after the typewriter) & writing in space has everything to do w/ RG's color holograph drawing poem project, r h y m m s. SENTENCES weighs about 6 pounds. In that sense, as something 'wanting to join nature by writing itself', it anyway attains mass/weight briefly.
      Cards typed by RG in Tufts U. English Dept. Office (via old RG teaching connection) on brand spanking new Selectric, as noted above, destroyed in production process (but see A.5. above). So be it! The 'gradual genesis' of the work itself can be traced, from RG notebooks of the period (in section I. above) through RG ts. versions (in IX.A.l-5. above). RG thanks Michael Waltuch.
      RG's work typing typewritten mss. by Larry Eigner/copying these for (potential) publication must be noted here too, beginning in Fall/Winter 1970-71, as drawing RG's literal attention to 'literature' w/in field of typewriter page.
  - B. A DAY AT THE BEACH, 1 box
    A DAY AT THE BEACH was designed/typed by RG, produced by Diane Ward (as a 70% reduction/offset from RG Selectric ts. images) & pub. by James Sherry's Roof Books in NYC in 1985 (says '1984' on copyright page but issued in early 1985) in a edition of 1000 (600?/RG's records show both) paperback copies, w/ photos of RG at beach on inside covers by Donald Guravich. It's 216 poems arranged (3 per page/6 on facing pages) on 6" by 10" pages, organized in 3 sections ("Morning", "Midday" & "Afternoon/Evening") w/ 72 poems each, making an account of an imaginary 'day' which moves through time but preserves/ opens multiple narrative possibilities (depending on how each reader 'travels' through 6 texts on facing pages), w/ 8 'testamonials' to work on back cover.
    COMMENT: A DAY THE BEACH/the present text, as chronicled in the materials above, was written 1980-1982 (probably also some from 1979, see RG Notebooks in section I. above), but its 'roots' go back, for RG, to waking up in the morning in Minnesota & looking to the West (the Norwegian side of RG's family had indeed 'gone West' (Augusta Bjeldanes was born in Oregon) but been driven back to Norwegian town of Madison, MN (almost on South Dakota border, west of RG's suburban home in Minneapolis) & RG's older brother, Judd, 'went West' from the U. of Minnesota to the U. of Cal. in Berkeley to 'graduate school' + everyone wanted to 'go West': for RG, to physically arrive at the/land's end/ water barrier, the Pacific Ocean--there, doubtless, was 'Life'/the 'second Nature' one was born for! And so (despite evidently being 'influenced' heavily by family matters & historical conditions) it has proved to be!
    Louis Zukofsky writes 'somewhere' "the lowly do not tune the senses' (quoting/translating someone?) (& this is 'a representative instance' of RG's 'scholarship'/laziness), but in fact RG has, over many years, beginning in 1968 (in complete consternation re what 'writing is', as shown in ms. in VII.A above) by getting out of town/driving out of Berkeley/U.C. west & south & exploring different ways to get to the beach/beaches/trails & what it 'felt like there' / what was 'interesting about it'. Rolling over & over in sand, swimming, writing "SAND" in the 'sand', was fun & a useful learning experience/combined w/ RG's daughter Amy's early language speaking & made the (all-too-readable) 'UR' version of A DAY AT THE BEACH (see VIII.F. & G. above), deservedly unpublished but bearing clear signs of a refocussing of attention/usage.
    Going back & back to the 'same beach' again (after a move back West in 1978 w /Amy), between Pigeon Point & Ano Neuvo Island in San Mateo County, on innumberable day trips from Oakland & Berkeley --bringing the 'method' forged in SENTENCES this time/language phenomena attention to what's going on--produced better results, if RG may say so. Important for writer to 'have a vocabulary'.
    Going back & back to the World, then, was established as a 'procedure' during this period (still going on, in RG day trips to RCA beach in Bolinas, 1999).
    The 'achieved Result' here is the ts./ms. in B.8. above, from which a facsimile edition should be made in time.
    Structurally, one can see further RG attempt (after OAKLAND (see XII.H below) & CAMBRIDGE M'ASS (XII.G.)), to reinhabit space/'format' of the 'book'/while allowing individual poems the 'whole world' they had in SENTENCES. This involved inventing a page design which would allow 6 individual poems on facing pages to be themselves AND 'telling a story' (or others making a 'story' otherwise) left-to-right/top-to-bottom & be history of an imagined 'day' (which is only turning pages of book themselves), in dutiful reading of imaginary facts of that place. (Some, in fact, were written back home in Berkeley.)
    Also, it's an investigation of possible 'times in the work' (see RG Reading & Discussion of A Day At The Beach in V.A.4. & V.C.3. above), an investigation of narrative including 3 different 'times'. (?)
    Seeking to write what happens at the edge of the World (see Robert Creeley note in III.B.7. above).
    "Fall/Winter Family Home" in RG's Series (made of 4 poems on 2 facing pages) provided RG w/ instigation/inspiration.
    - 1. Envelope containing ca. 609 RG ts. poems gathered from notebooks toward book, from 1980-82 (Box 21)
      w/ RG holograph note "NARRATION / for Bernadette Mayer" re time in the 'day' written on outside of envelope (155 pp. total)
    - 2. Oxford Index Card box w/ "A DAY AT THE BEACH" (Box 21)
      Written on top, containing 386 RG Selectric ts. poems centered on 386 5" by 8" index cards.
      - "Better Rejects 8/4/82", (22 cards/poems)
      - "Rejects 8/4/82", (364 cards/poems)
    - 3. Oxford Index Card box w/ "A DAY AT THE BEACH / 'second state' / (8/4/82)" (Box 21)
      Includes other information re design of the work written on top, containing 216 RG Selectric ts. poems centered on 216 5" by 8" index cards (219 cards total w/ section headings), numbered on backs, w/ top card inside bearing RG holograph note outlining design of "BEACH POEM" (being RG preliminary model for book eventually produced)
    - 4. RG Selectric ts. master for RG-produced 1st edition of A DAY AT THE BEACH (see B.5. below) w/ pages numbered on backs & arranged in sequence necessary for xeroxing 1st ed., w/ page design materials & RG holograph master image for cover/title page (86 pp. total) (ca. 1983) (Box 21)
    - 5. Copy of RG-produced 1st edition of A DAY AT THE BEACH (unnumbered, one of 40 made in ca. 1983) (Box 21)
      216 poems arranged (3 per page) on 72 8½" by 14" pages, w/ section headings (80 pp. total), stapled in brown covers (produced by RG on Kodak copier in Berkeley & given to friends) (RARE / SAVE !)
    - 6. Envelope containing Diane Ward ts. letter to RG, May 21, 1994 (Box 21)
      Reproduction of Roof Books edition of A DAY AT THE BEACH, enclosing Charles Bernstein xerox reduction from RG-produced 1st edition (in B.5. above) toward 6" by 9" Roof format then under consideration (too small!)
    - 7. Envelope containing Diane Ward ts. letter to RG, June 14, 1984 (Box 21)
      Regarding legibility problems ensuing from reduction to 70% from RG-produced masters for 1st edition, acknowledging agreed-upon 6" by 10" page format (a compromise/RG wanted 6" by 11"), enclosing 2 sample pages (1 typeset) & proposing to resolve problems by typesetting ms. (RG wanted to preserve typewriter spacing which, after basis established in SENTENCES, was then crucial to thinking/ procedure in RG poems, & so set about re-typing whole ms. w/ bigger letter images on better Selectric, see B.8. below)
    - 8. RG Selectric ts. master for Roof Books edition of A DAY AT THE BEACH, 216 poems arranged (3 per page) on 72 8½" by 14" pages, w/ 3 section headings (80 pp. total) + page design material, w/ pages numbered on backs, sent to Diane Ward in Summer 1994 to make 70% reduction for offset edition pub. by Roof in 1985 (RARE / SAVE !) (this--rather than either pub. Roof book or RG-produced 1st ed.--is true/real 'achieved form' of this work & should be used in future to make facsimile/8½" by 14" edition of A DAY AT THE BEACH!) (Box 21)
    - 9. Folder containing 4 pages from RG Selectric ts. master for Roof edition (in B.8. above) + 4 70% reductions made from same by RG, to test legibility of new masters at 70% reduction (Box 21)
      (much better / decision to make book with these)
    - 10. Xerox of RG holograph letter to DW, September 27, 1984 (Box 21)
      Enclosing 8 'testamonials' to work (compiled by RG from solicited statements & letters previously sent RG re 1st ed.) for use on back cover + Donald Guravich photos for inside covers (9 pp. total)
    - 11. Envelope containing DW holograph letter to RG, November 7, 1984 (Box 21)
      Enclosing page proofs for book (text & photos, w/ RG holograph annotations), DW holograph letter to RG, November 16, 1984 re cover colors & DW holograph letter to RG, December 13, 1984 (on back of further proofs of photos for inside covers) (89 pp. total)
    - 12. Folder containing contract materials, between James Sherry/ Roof Books & RG re book, July 1985, (12 pp. total) (Box 21)
      - JS holograph note to RG, July 1985
        Enclosing contract for book (written contract needed for National Endowment for the Arts grant purposes)
      - Xerox of RG holograph letter to JS, July 14, 1985
        re contract
      - Xerox of RG holograph letter to JS, July 22, 1985
      - Xerox of contract, as modified by RG & signed by RG only
        (RG has in his possession contract signed by both RG & JS w/ "600 copies" changed to "1000 copies", apparently by JS holograph.
  - C. PHANTOM ANTHEMS, 1 box
    PHANTOM ANTHEMS was designed/typed & produced by RG (as an 82% reduction/offset from RG Selectric ts. images) & pub. by Leslie Scalapino's 0 Books (as the 1st 0 Books book) & RG in 1986 in an edition of 1,000 (unnumbered) paperback copies (LS financed the 1st 600/RG the remainder), w/ covers designed by LS. It was written between 1982 & 1986 & consists of 118 poems variously arranged on 7½" by 9" acid-free pages in 9 sections (112 pp. total)
    COMMENT: To RG's surprise, although some poems in PHANTOM ANTHEMS echoed the methods/concerns of those in A DAY AT THE BEACH & a few were written in late afternoon/early evening (in westward-facing grasslands in the Berkeley hills), most were written indoors/in the kitchen at 2338 McGee Ave., Berkeley on loose 8½" by 11" sheets of paper (rather than the various notebooks which had been (& are now again) the basis of RG's practice) between 4 & 7 in the morning, in a condition of exhaustion/exasperation & (even) 'moral outrage' recovering as possible from RG's night shift as a legal proofreader in the 'belly of the beast' (which 'organ' was 25 floors in the air in the San Francisco financial district, a 'skyscraper' w/ sealed/plate glass 'views' of the very Bay Area 'real estate' the language of capitalism RG was helping to repair/activate (e.g. in shopping center leases) was gathering itself through the night into a sticky mass of Jaundice & Jarndyce-like provisions & provisos to utterly/completely destroy) where RG worked for a big corporate law firm 'to the best of his ability' some 28 hours per week for 16 years. Shocking. The language & subject matter of PHANTOM ANTHEMS directly reflect/ embody the material conditions of this new environment ('new' to RG!) where 'personnel' are but further/'human' 'resources' to be ground up into cash/sucked dry & discarded/terminated when profit-making potential's past (e.g. elimination of 'proofreading function' by BP & H in. May 1998, restoring 7 'oldtimers' to the pavement) ---i.e. there's a lot of legal diction, arguments w/ everything & everyone, hortatory bombast (Whitman's "puff"), rants against 'ills of civilization' etc. even more excessive (as usage, throwing more & 'wrong' words into the charm) than those RG was 'processing' in 'Document Processing' (as if, thereby, to cause the whole business to 'explode/ implode' & 'save the World?), contrasted w/ patient studies of dawn/light coming/walnut tree & roses visible life & 'values' evident yet out backyard window, 7 a.m.
    So that strange night work gave RG vision of morning / specificity of things piecing themselves together out from 'naught' (reversing focus on, essentially, sun going down in beach poem), as well, & it was quiet in house then (w/ Amy, Kathleen Frumkin, KF's son Ezra & Larry Eigner (for whom RG was also working) asleep), to write.
    And, there were xerox machines (many of them) at BP & H, so that RG was able to (learn to) struggle to produce the 82% reduction (from RG ts. original) documented above, from which offset master for book was made.
    - 1. Envelope containing 57 RG holograph drafts of poems in PHANTOM ANTHEMS, in the order in which they occur in book, written 1982-85, (83 pp. total) (Box 22)
    - 2. Envelope containing 98 RG tss. of poems in PHANTOM ANTHEMS, in the order in which they occur in book, from ca. 1984-85, (110 pp. total) (Box 22)
    - 3. RG ts. of ms. called TWENTY-SIX POEMS, submitted w/ RG's successful application for a National Endowment for the Arts Fellowship, February 29, 1984, (& xerox of same), being a draft of eventual 1st section of PHANTOM ANTHEMS/ showing stage of project at that time (42 pp. total) (Box 22)
    - 4. RG ms. called "PHANTOM ANTHEMS / (1st state/June 1985)", being a xerox of RG ts. (w/ RG holograph revisions), (81 pp. total) (Box 22)
    - 5. RG ms. called "PHANTOM ANTHEMS / 2nd state/October 1985", xerox of RG ts. (w/ RG holograph revisions), (93 pp. total) (Box 22)
    - 6. RG ms. called "PHANTOM ANTHEMS / 3rd state/l985", being a xerox of RG ts. (w/ RG holograph revisions), (112 pp. total) (Box 22)
    - 7. RG ms. called "PHANTOM ANTHEMS / 4th state/December 1985", xerox of RG ts. (w/ RG holograph revisions), (112 pp. total) (Box 22)